<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>x
            <!--<!-\- can informally produce a prose description -\->
            <p>Information about the source</p>-->

            <title>Encoding the Gettysburg Address</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Produced as a homework assignment for class</resp>
               <persName corresp="#MJB">Mikol Bailey</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>

         <publicationStmt>
            <!--<!-\- can informally produce a prose description -\->
            <p>Information about the publication</p>-->

            <publisher>Self-published <note>Created as part of a class exercise</note>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2023-02-21">February 21, 2023</date>
            <idno/>
            <availability>
               <licence>a license</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <!--<!-\- Mikol made this transcription in about a half hour before class, and hopes it is okay. -\->
            <p>Mikol is auditing this class, so it's alright if their performance is less than stellar, I hope.</p>-->

            <bibl>
               <title>President Lincoln's Address at Gettysburg</title>
               <publisher>San Francisco Bulletin <note>Published as Daily Evening Bulletin</note>
               </publisher>
               <date when="1863-12-18">December 18, 1863</date>
               <biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Applause lines are labeled in this transcription. Punctuation and spellings have been
               maintained within the transcription. Words or phrases that are deemed indecipherable
               have been noted as "[illegible]," and letters that are deemed indecipherable have
               been noted as "_."</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="newspaper">
            <head>President Lincoln's Address at Gettysburg</head>
            <p>The consecration of the Soldiers' Cemetery at Gettysburg, Pa. <!-- ... --> He
               said:</p>
            <p>Four scores and seven years ago our fathers established upon this continent a
               government subscribed in liberty and dedicated to the fundamental principles that all
               men are created equal by a good God. <incident><desc>[Applause]</desc></incident> Now we are
               engaged in a great contest—the question whether this nation, any nation, so
               conceived, so educated, can long remain. We are met on a great battle-field of the
               war; we are met here to dedicate a portion of that field as the final resting place
               of those who have given their lives that the nation might live. It is all right,
               befitting and proper, that we should do this—but in a larger sense, we cannot
               dedicate—we cannot consecrate—we cannot hallow this ground. The brave and
               self-sacrificing men, living and dead, who struggled here, have consecrated it far
               above our power to add or detract. <incident><desc>[Great applause.]</desc></incident> The dead
               will little heed. Let us long remember what we have, but not forget what they did
               here. <incident><desc>[Immense applause.]</desc></incident>, nor long remember, what we say here,
               but it can never forget It is for us the, rather—the living—to be dedicated here to
               the unfinished work that they have thus far so nobly carried forward.
                  <incident><desc>["G__d," and great applause.]</desc></incident>It is better for us to be
               dedivated to the great task remaining before us: for [illegible] to renew our
               devotion to that cause for which they gave the full measure of their devotion. Here
               let us resolve that what they have done shall not have been done in vain; that the
               nation shall, under God, have a new birth; and that Government of the people; founded
               by the people, for the people, shall not perish.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
